Matt Hag sold more than 10 million
copies of his book, The Midnight
Library. And I just checked on Amazon.
It has more than 288,000
reviews. This book was a total hit, a
smashing success. So, I invited Matt on
the show to ask him how he does it.
What's his writing process? How does he
tell great stories? But also, given how
successful he's been, I had to ask, is
it okay to write for the mass market?
Like, are you betraying the craft of
writing if you're explicitly trying to
reach as many people [music] as
possible?
Can you walk me through how a book
actually gets written? Like how long
does it take? Where do you write? When
do you write? Are you somebody who
writes 250 words every day? A thousand
words every day? Are you a little bit
more stop start?
>> I'm totally stop start. I'm a lot of
stop. [laughter]
Like it's weird because I'm seen as
prolific, but I spend most of
>> a lot of stop. A little bit [laughter]
of start. A lot of stop. A little bit of
start.
>> Yeah, it's 90% stop. That's it.
But I'm I it's a very I swing between
two extremes. So a lot of it is trying
to think of an idea.
Writer's block for me is not knowing
which idea to choose.
>> I don't have a a great detector at
knowing which idea is going to work. I
have to sort of end up writing them to
know. But they linger in my brain until
they're developed enough to write.
>> And these are story ideas, character
ideas. What kind of ideas? story ideas
sometimes titles just hanging there
which I think that's a good title but I
just need an idea for it like for ages I
was I had this uh title the memory thief
but I thought who's memory who's the
thief wh why why is this in my head and
you know so you you can have a title
without an idea but sometimes the
title's the thing that comes last it
just depends but a lot of it is just
percolating in your in your brain so
there's a lot of work that doesn't feel
like work and you're sort of beating
yourself up because you think why aren't
they working but actually that turns out
to be the most important work because
you are actually thinking about stuff
and it's that classic thing like when
you're sat in front of a word document
you just can't get inspiration so you
you need to be away it's often when I'm
in another country or when I'm traveling
that I'll just get an idea it it you
need to be taken out of yourself a
little
to get it. So, I swing from that sort of
state of thinking and percolating and
beating myself up about not working
while secretly working to then getting
the idea and then uh worried that I
won't remember it all. And that's when I
sort of rush and uh write and have the
impulse to write because it's the
impulse to get it all down while it's
still in your head.
and then first draft revision, working
with an editor. How does that go?
>> Um, well, I've had the same editor for
15 years now. So, I think it really
helps to have a good relationship with
your ed editor because then you know
them. You know their taste. You know
when to listen to them and when to sort
of fight your own corner. Um, and you
you you know when they're saying
something which a general reader would
think versus when it's them as a person,
you know what I mean? So you know them
well enough know what is their specific
taste versus what could be a general
point that lots of people would make. So
um it's a lot of conversations, a lot of
phone conversations, a lot of back and
forth. He's a nice guy, my editor,
Francis Bikmore. Um and so he's
sometimes a bit too nice. So, I have to
get to what he's actually saying. I say
be a bit more brutal. Uh, I know how to
translate what he's saying and what he
means. And sometimes in editing, it's
easier to be brutal. Um, because often
like there's a temptation to sort of
like correct sentences and correct lines
and correct a little scene when really
there's a bigger problem. It's not the
thing that's happening on that specific
page. it's actually speaking to a bigger
problem. What famously happens um with
me and my editor is he will say a few
things thinking I'm going to change a
paragraph here, a paragraph there, and
then suddenly I'll have wiped out 50,000
words cuz I'm just like, you know, if if
you're spotting a little problem there,
I'm going to like pull at that and
think, what is that problem about? Oh,
it's about that whole character doesn't
need to be there or that whole premise.
I mean, with a novel I write called The
Humans, I think I deleted
40, it was a small novel to start with.
It was about 80,000 words. And so 40,000
of those went and then another 55,000
were added between the first and second
draft. And and it's strange because you
will click send on your first draft
thinking it's the most perfect,
complete, finished thing that you can
do. you think you actually feel like it
isn't a first draft because you've got
you've known it and you've gone through
it and you've been editing as you go.
>> You've lived inside of it.
>> You've lived inside of it. So, it's it's
called technically a first draft, but it
doesn't actually feel like a first draft
in your head. It feels like something
you've just gone through and gone
through and you think this time my
editor is going to faint in wonder and
think this is perfect but nothing to do.
And obviously that's not what happens.
What happens is that that there is stuff
to do, but it's needed those outside
eyes to see it. And it's an interesting
art editing because you have to go in
knowing there's no such thing as
perfection. You have to go in knowing
there's no perfect novel that you can
reach. And also understanding that there
comes a point that each draft you're
improving things
could start to make it worse. Like
there's a diminishing returns that
happens with me. is like the fourth or
fifth round after that
you're you're getting so far away from
the thing you started with that it's
getting worse and you see it in the film
industry all the time when things have
just been too meddled with
>> and this is a lot of people's complaint
about electronic music I was getting a
haircut yesterday just listening to
super pop EDM and I was like it feels
flat it's too perfect you know like all
the notes hit on the fours and the
eights
>> and there's none of the you know we go
out to a pub here in London tonight and
you hear some of the like a really good
live band. There's a messiness, there's
a chaos that kind of comes from it that
is very human,
>> but something about it feels more alive.
>> Yeah, exactly. And this is my one and
only optimistic take about AI is it's
going to make humans be more human.
We're going to realize we can't do what
AI is doing and we don't work like AI.
We're actually work like the opposite of
AI. We're going to become more human and
I feel like the taste is going to be for
weirder stuff. If you think about what
AI is, AI is looking at everything
that's gone before. True creativity is
going to become more valuable, i.e.
creating new stuff, things that AI can't
do because it doesn't exist and it's
only knowing what's existed and we're
trying to create things that haven't
existed. So I think this sort of trend
of looking backwards at what trends were
and what things eventually isn't going
to work anymore because AI can do all of
that. We're going to have to find new
messy human things. And it's interesting
to me from the sort of creative
standpoint to look at the difference
fundamentally different nature of AI to
human evolution. Like life famously
evolves through mistakes and mutations
and that's how DNA works. Whereas AI is
set up to be a perfectionist. It sort of
wheels out all mistakes. Any equivalent
of mutation it stops. So we evolve in
fundamentally opposite ways. Life and
technology evolves in fundamentally
opposite ways. And I think there's a
sort of optimism there that actually
being human is something quite different
that AI won't be able to replicate
because we we we create more beautiful
mistakes.
>> So take me forward 20, 30 years.
We're looking at the books that people
are reading. How are they different in
that world where AI is all around us
than the books that we're reading now?
I mean
I have no idea but [laughter]
so I know that but the romantic in you
will answer this question in me will
answer this question and say that I
think for me personally and for a lot of
people the moment you know a human
hasn't created something a human hasn't
felt something a human hasn't gone
through the pain that's being written
about then it becomes somehow how
automatically less or redundant. Like
>> part of me when I'm hearing a song, when
I'm watching a film, when I'm seeing an
actor, when I'm reading a book, part of
that power is knowing there's a humanity
behind it, knowing there's an
articulation. You know, I felt a lot
like everyone, I felt a lot of pain in
my life. And one of the reasons I'm
drawn to art is to ease that pain and to
feel understood and feel less alone. And
if art is there to make us feel less
alone, then how is AI, which is making
us feel more alone, going to help with
that? We're going to need other humans
more, we're going to need art more as
our world changes in the face of
technology. So the romantic in me feels
that books made by humans even if it
becomes like you know humanmade as a
sticker like organic or fair trade
onward I think there will always be a uh
value of being human for humans. So art
will always have its place as a human
form. This is what I hope. I hope that
things become out of sheer rarity maybe,
but as we're more clogged up, as our
inboxes and as the internet is more
clogged up with this artificial stuff,
the our eyes and ears will be so much
more craving um the sort of beautiful
inauthentic
authentic messy chaos.
>> I'm so desperate for it, man. just like
to read writing where when I read it, I
feel the voice, the soul, the
personality of whoever that is on the
other side where it's like I'm getting
you. I'm getting Matt. I'm getting David
in this email and I can feel your
presence through these words.
>> And I think we'll be more forgiving of
mistakes. I think we'll be more
forgiving of imperfections. We might,
you know, like uh young people have
famously been feeling this pressure
about looking perfect and everything
else and and that's going to fade away,
I think, because we we're going to
realize we either fail to compete with
AI or we just value what we are
inherently in ourselves. And I think
that's the only way we can go.
>> When you think of school, what comes to
mind? For me, it was lectures, homework,
sitting at a desk. And the worst part is
it doesn't even work. 54% of Americans
read below a sixth grade level. That's
over half of Americans. We need
something new. And that's why I'm
excited to have Alpha School as the
flagship sponsor for How I Write. At
Alpha, you go to school and do all your
academics at only 2 hours per day. So
that then you can spend the rest of the
day learning life skills like launching
a business, writing a musical, or giving
a TED talk. You know, the kind of things
that make you a capable and well-rounded
person. and it's working. They have
academics figured out. Alpha classes
test in the top 1% nationally and more
than 90% of alpha students say they love
school. Now, I used to live in Austin
where alpha school started and I was
consistently blown away with what was
happening there. [music] I personally
mentored a bunch of Alpha students and
what stood out to me is how much the
team believes in the potential of kids
way more than what I ever got in school.
Alpha's approach and the success it's
already having is why it's the most
talked about K- through2 school in the
world right now. And it's also where I
want to send my kids to school one day.
So, if you want to learn more, go to
go.alpha.school/h
how I write.
What I hope doesn't happen is that it
becomes like modern art where it becomes
about the shock and it becomes about the
novelty and it becomes about look at
what I did that no one else has ever
done before.
>> Yeah. Right. Right. Right. Yeah, but I I
I think again that that you know AI
could almost replicate that. I feel like
true human feeling like when I'm talking
about creating something new, it's not
like you know coming up with a new form,
a new media. It's literally just trying
to articulate emotions in a way that
haven't been articulated before or a
story that has been told in a different
way. Because if you're not creating
something
new, if you're creating things that have
already been written exactly as they
are, then where's the impulse to write
them? You might as well just, you know,
read what's already been. So, I think
it's essentially, you know, creativity
is essentially anti-AII
from the get-go because it's about
creating stuff that's not there.
You think about short words and long
words and you have a line that I like
that sparrows fly higher than peacocks.
>> Oh yeah, I do like short words. My
favorite word is probably home. I like
sky. I like love. I like mono syllables.
I think in British writing tradition,
certainly in the last 100 years, we're
encouraged to always value the less used
word. Um, and I'm quite the opposite.
But I can remember at school my English
teacher always used to say, you know,
you must never use nice. You must never
say the word nice. And I think why?
Because people do use the word nice. And
I actually like the word nice. It can it
can be a lazy word, but nice is a word
with lots of sort of subtleties to it as
well. So, I don't think there's any word
that you definitely shouldn't use by
virtue of it being overused. I just
think it's how you use it. And I also
think there's something very accessible
about simple words. And if you've got a
word like home or sky, it's just got an
infinite sort of archetypal power to it.
I think that's just everyone has their
own understanding of it.
>> An infinite archetypal power. What do
you mean by that? Well, I mean like if
we think about the power of language
being something that brings people
together and connects people, then
within language, the most simple
concepts and the most simple words are
possibly the most powerful ones cuz
they're the most shared and they're the
most understood. And I always find, I
don't know why, but if you end a chapter
of a book with one of those words like
sky or home, it just leaves on a nice
little note of kind of universality.
>> Mhm. What is it that you love about
first drafts but then get frustrated
with in the editing process?
>> A first draft is new. You know, if you
think about a novel being something new,
I mean, that's why you're writing a
novel. That's what a novel means. That's
why, you know, the impulse to write is
to put something new into the world. A
first draft, everything is new. It's new
to you. So, that's as close as you'll
get to being a reader of your novel in
the first draft because you're sort of
reading from your own imagination and
dictating what's there. So I like first
drafts because they're not boring to
write. Whereas editing can become by its
very nature monotonous, repetitive and
familiar. Whereas uh when you're writing
a first draft, you're sort of you're
fishing your own imagination. You're
like on the banks of your own
imagination and you're um waiting to see
what's there. Because I've written
non-fiction and fiction. And the
difference between writing non-fiction
in first draft and fiction is that with
non-fiction you are confined to
literally what you know and not just
that to what you absolutely know you
know. Whereas with fiction I think it's
much more mysterious. I think you're
writing what you know but you're writing
what you don't know you know. So you're
sort of waiting to see what's there and
and you sort of discover more things
about yourself and your imagination.
It's it's like entering your own dreams,
isn't it? Fiction versus non-fiction
where you're in the land of sort of
shared objective reality, whereas
fiction is much sort of like trippier in
a way and you're going into your sort of
own subconscious.
>> Wow. The idea of entering your own dream
is crazy. Describe that.
Well, like I think it doesn't happen all
the time, but you can reach a kind of
like flow state in the middle of writing
a first draft where you're not
consciously
thinking around the writing. You're not
sort of aware of what you're doing.
You're just writing. If you're doing
anything often enough and you're getting
proficient at it, you can reach a point
where it's becoming quite unconscious.
And I've noticed with writing fiction,
that's the point where interesting stuff
can happen, where it's almost automatic
and is not planned. I'm not a planner.
I, you know, I like to know roughly what
I'm writing. I like to have a title. I
like to know a concept and my
characters, but beyond that, I'm not
someone who sort of linearly writes down
chronological order what what's going
on.
>> So then when you're when it's working
for you, what are you feeling?
um
a feeling like excitement, but I but
there's also a kind of
anxiety that sets in and a kind of
feeling of like putting pressure on
yourself because with me it is
equivalent to being a reader in a in the
sense that you you have a story in your
mind and you're trying to dictate it and
you're experiencing it for the first
time and you're rushing in in the sense
that you're trying to get it all down
before you forget it. So, you have the
book in your head and you've got the
sort of duty to get it down before it's
gone. This is my problem with first
drafts. I I generally love first drafts,
but my problem with them is that mine
tend to be quite rushed, you know? It's
like a six-year-old coming in to say
what just happened in the sand pit and
like saying and then and then Sammy
pushed me over and this happened and
that happened and then and then and
then. So every sentence pretty much
starts with and then you know I was just
sort of garbled writing it writing it
rush. I even have and then tattooed on
my wrist [laughter]
just to remind me that this is something
I do. I possibly shouldn't but there's
an always and then in life but um yeah
so and then is is my is my weakness of
just like always s of like uh rushing.
But uh the flip side is that that that
[sighs]
[gasps]
means you're sort of like not lingering
on stuff you don't need to linger on.
You're getting the story down and then
you can embellish in the sort of editing
process.
>> So implied in what you're saying is the
thing that is
pulling you is the plot, the story.
Well, I suppose with me, with my
writing, I want people to feel something
and to to get something out of it that's
slightly more than a story, but the
story is the vehicle to get them there
to that feeling. So, I feel like for me,
a story is a way of carrying an emotion,
a thought
in the best way that I can manage to
deliver it to someone else.
>> So, break that down how that would show
up differently in different books for
you. Even though I'm seen as quite a I
think quite an uplifting optimistic
writer in recent years in my earlier
books they were quite depressing. I mean
I wrote a book my third book which you
won't have read no one has read. It's
called the possession of Mr. Cave. It's
like the most depressing book I think
anyone's ever written. Everyone dies in
it. There's literally no hope. I would
recommend no one to read this book. But
it was [laughter]
it was it it wasn't badly written. I
don't think it was just so pointless and
so depressing.
And I was quite depressed when I was
writing it. So So I that is an example
of the extreme, you know, how how you
can ex feel extremely low and that be
reflected in the work. Now when I'm
writing something uplifting, it's not
because I'm feeling necessarily really
happy. It's because I'm wanting to do
something a bit more difficult than when
I was younger and actually to to go into
sort of like the tricky areas of life
and try and find some sort of authentic
optimism.
Not an easy optimism, not all unicorns
and rainbows, but to try and find
something within the reality and
depression and darkness of life, but to
try and find some light or hope in there
just because basically I think that's a
more useful thing to do with the one
life we have to actually put something
that can gives give someone a little bit
of hope or a little bit of uh optimism.
>> We're talking about what pulls you as a
writer. How would a premise pull you?
Cuz a question that's being asked, an
idea that you're exploring.
>> Yeah, a concept uh for me is everything.
Like uh if I get a concept that seems
simple enough that I can just articulate
it quite easily in a sentence, I think,
okay, that that's good. That's I'm not
having to overthink the concept. It's
there is neat. you know, doesn't happen
often, but when you get it, you kind of
uh
>> like Midnight Library for
>> Midnight Library was definitely one
where I thought that is a very uh simple
idea, but I had that idea for a long
time. It became simpler when I had the
title because for a while I didn't have
the title. I just had this idea of a
library. I think the original title was
the library of lost lives which would
have been much too sort of long and
uh a bit I don't know pretentious but
the midnight library just shrunk it and
just made it a simpler concept. So that
was an example of a sort of like the
right title simplifying the concept.
>> What's wrong with pretentious?
Um there's nothing wrong with like
uh
difficulty or complexity,
but when it's
just to sort of impress for no other
purpose than just to impress and say,
"Aren't I a clever person? Aren't I a
clever writer?" Then I think, what's the
point of it? Um so, and it's a trait I
used to have when I started out. I think
there's two two temptations a writer has
that can make you go wrong or go off
track or stop you being yourself. One is
the desire
to be too popular, too
liked, too uh you you know too much of a
people pleaser on the page. And the
other thing is to desire to be taken
seriously to
I don't know to be seen as a proper
writer to be awards worthy to get the
big reviews and that at various points
in my career I've fallen victim to both
of those traps I feel um out of certain
insecurities at different points. So the
commercial trap I suppose and then the
capital L literary trap and to write
purely
I think you kind of just have to just
find a sort of inner voice that is
immune to both of those temptations and
that doesn't mean that someone else
reading it might think oh this is too
commercial or this is too literary or
this is too pretentious but it means you
writing it wrote it from a pure place.
At what point in your career did you
feel like you could transcend at least
the commercial instincts? Did you come
out of the gate saying I need to make
money from this?
>> Well, one very simple uh
understanding is that the moment you
try and be commercial or try and
research a market is the moment you will
fail to be commercial and fail to reach
the market. So there's a paradox
inherent in that. I notice in publishing
a lot and it's understandable and it's
there in every industry that it becomes
quite backwards looking by its nature.
trends will be dictated on the basis of
what sold last year and even what sold
last year is actually going further back
in time because it was um taken on and
edited two years ago and written 3 years
ago and conceived four five years ago or
a decade ago. So by looking at the
market going out and just looking at the
tables in a bookstore you're just
looking at the past really. You're not
looking at if you started writing a book
now and that book's all right. It's
going to be on tables in 5 years time.
So that's not the market. That's that's
the past from where you're going to be.
So So thinking commercially,
I don't even know what that means in
that sense because we don't know the
future of the market. So you the only
reader you're going to know is yourself.
So you just have to be honest about the
book you would want to read and that you
would want to write. And hopefully those
two things are the same thing. And when
that happens, then that's one to do.
>> What if I came to you and I was like,
dude, I am being honest. Like, I think
this is good. It's just it's just not
working. No one is buying what I'm
making. Help me. That was my situation.
like I I was the the big sort of
breakthrough novel I suppose for me was
The Midnight Library, but that was like
book number 20 in terms of everything.
Um, so I had written a lot of books. I'd
been rejected by a lot of publishers.
I'd been dropped by a couple of
publishers, but still
I had to just find what I wanted to
write because I had no no other way to
write. And I'm very ADHD.
So for me, I can't write what I don't
want to write cuz I'm just too bored.
You know, I I I can't just be motivated
by a deadline or necessity. I have to
actually enjoy it because, you know,
otherwise I get too distracted and I
there's more interesting things. So it
has to be the most interesting thing for
me to write. And often actually one of
the best things for me in terms of my
career was being dropped because I was
dropped by a publisher. A tough point in
my life cuz we just had our first child
and we had zero money and lots of debt.
So we had a lot of financial pressure
which would make you think you were
going to try and write something safe
and commercial. But that was the point.
For some strange reason I just wrote my
first attempt at ignoring all that. I
wrote a book which had elements of
science fiction, was strange tonally. It
went from comedy to serious. It had an
alien in it as a central character. It
was called The Humans. It was a very odd
book to write at that time. It didn't
fit in the market because it wasn't pure
science fiction. It wasn't a pure
literary book. It wasn't purely comedy.
It wasn't purely romantic. It was lots
of different things, but it was very
much me and all my influences in one
sort of pot. And that became at that
point, certainly in the UK,
by far my most successful book. Because
I'd been dropped, I was had a kind of
like Devil May Care feeling like, well,
probably no one's going to read this
anyway, so if I'm writing something, I
might as well just write it for me. And
often when you get into that mode and
you feel a little bit of nervousness in
your stomach about what you're writing,
that tends to be the one. When you lean
into the nervousness, the anxiety, the
self-consciousness, and actually just
push past it, that's the point at which
you think, "Oh, this is going to work
for me."
With that book, what stood out to me was
something I see over and over is this
idea of you're going to write about
something that's disconnected from you,
but then in that disconnection, you then
have the freedom to write about things
that are very intimate.
>> Yes.
>> Talk to me about that.
>> Totally. Well, yeah. Like that was
weirdly my most personal book. The
Humans was my most personal book, but it
was also my most fantastical in the
sense that it was literally about an
alien from another planet coming to
Earth to destroy humanity. So, it wasn't
my life.
Weirdly, it wasn't my life. But it also
was an example of when you're writing
fiction, discovering things about
yourself that you don't know about
yourself. And this in quite a literal
sense, like a lot of people read that
book and said to me, "Oh, thank you for
writing a fable of autism. Thank you for
writing a book about what it feels like
to be autistic." I was like, I hadn't
written a book about autism. What are
you talking about? And then years later,
after my son, who who presented very
clearly as autist diagnosed with autism,
I went along thinking I was just going
to get diagnosed with ADHD and then I
was the psychiatrist also told me I was
autistic. I was thinking maybe I was
maybe I was writing
about what it feels like to be neurode
divergent via this alien in a human body
who doesn't understand human rules. And
maybe that's what I was writing, but I
didn't know I was writing that. I
thought I was writing Douglas Adams
tribute about an alien coming to Earth.
And but that's what I find addictive
about creating stuff. I I think that
unknown
sort of lagoon that you're sort of like
sat beside and then watching things
bubble up. Yeah. That's what's sort of
tantalizing about it. You know, there's
a point in your career where it becomes
a career where there's contracts,
there's deadlines, there's advances,
there's expectation, there's a
readership. And then you start to think,
you start to question, am I writing for
the right reasons? Am I do I would I
still be a writer if this wasn't a job
and this was a hobby? Would I still go
away and just write stories? You never
100% know the honest answer to that. But
I think genuinely in my case I would
because after the Midnight Library I had
a kind of mental health wobble. I gave
up alcohol. I um had therapy for the
first time in my life. I should have had
it about 20 years before
>> after the book came out. after the book
came out
>> after it was successful. Uh well it was
successful but I I don't think it was to
do with that necessarily other than the
fact that
>> when you have success you can have this
sort of sudden guilt if you're not
feeling happy all the time cuz you're
like other people think well what have
you got to worry about but my yeah you
know I had various stuff my dad was
going through cancer um we we my son was
ill for a while and you know just lots
of life stresses were going on
simultaneously at the same time this
other great dream was being fulfilled
and I had this big successful novel. So,
it was just a lot. It was it was it was
a sort of time to get therapy. But I
also thought that was possibly the time
to step away from writing. I thought I
don't need to write in the way I used to
for, you know, as a job. I could step
away for a while. I could just sort of
leave it there. And so, I had about 6
months to a year not writing.
But I found
I had nowhere to sort of like hook
myself to sort of like place this energy
in in terms of my own mind. And so I did
end up writing and I wrote a very
strange novel called of a life
impossible. And that I feel it was
almost like writing a first novel again
because I I was genuinely writing that
for me. It wasn't a very outward-f
facing novel. It wasn't a very reader
centric novel. It was just me getting
stuff out and um but it was it was kind
of therapy. It was kind of like just
ordering the world in a way that I
couldn't otherwise.
Yeah. What are the adjectives that you
feel like you're embodying when you're
pulled into a story? Is it curiosity? Is
it play? Is it wonder? Is it kind of
like fantastical?
>> I do like fantasy and I like realism,
but I like having one foot in both. But
my my safe space, the place I like to
work in is where it's a recognizable
real world, but something odd is going
on within that real world. And I also
think now in like um the 2020s it's
increasingly hard I feel some people can
do it very well to write about objective
reality because I feel like in the
internet age in our increasingly divided
society it's hard to agree to have a
consensus to have a unifying idea of
what reality
is. And how would this show up in a
novel?
>> Well, in a novel,
the re the way the reason I like to
write a sort of recognizable reality
that has something surreal happening in
it or something that couldn't quite
necessarily happen is because I think
that is almost more realistic to me now
because we're all in our own little
reality bubbles that aren't necessarily
capital R reality. So it seems almost
arrogant I feel to just sort of write a
novel and say this is reality or this is
what London is or British life is
because it's like I feel everyone has a
different version of what that is.
Whereas when you're write putting a
little bit of fantasy in there, you're
suddenly entering the land of uh dreams
and I feel like dreams are not only
safer in that sense, they're also
uh more revealing and you can actually
you can bring um very different types of
readers together. I think the thing I'm
proudest most of in terms of my career
is that I don't have a specific
reader. Like when I I do a book event,
I've got, you know, men, women, young
people, old people, you know, I don't
have a specific reader. And that I think
for me is the thing I'm proudest of. But
I don't have a set demographic because
what I'm trying to do when I'm writing
is to try and reach that level of shared
empathy and understanding between
people.
>> Mhm. How did writing children's books
help you get there?
>> Writing children's books to me is the
purest kind of writing. Um I feel like
children genuinely are the best readers
in the sense that they are so close to
their imaginations. So yes, obviously if
you're writing the children's books,
there's stuff you can't write about and
shouldn't write about and you have to be
aware of that. And also there's a sense
of responsibility when you're writing
for children. But at the same time,
there's also great freedom because
children are so willing to go with the
daydream. They're so willing. You can
have a sort of real world setting. You
can set a novel in London and then have
a unicorn walk down the street and the
child will be so willing to believe in
that unicorn [laughter] that they will
go with a unicorn. If you do that in an
adult novel, you would have to have an
essay on quantum physics about how it
could be possible. And to the extent,
this is how much I value writing for
children and children as readers. If I'm
stuck writing a novel for adults, I try
and think what would be the children's
story version of this. So with like the
last book I I wrote, The Midnight Train,
the first draft of which was very adult.
It was actually about AI. It was a sort
of AI dystopian story and it just wasn't
working at all. And I thought, what
could I bring from sort of like
children's literature? And that, you
know, children's books often have a
magical train or railways in them. It's
kind of like, you know, the railway
children, Harry Potter, you've got um
Polar Express. Yeah. You've got a lot of
magic trains in children's books. So,
that was one of the things that led me
towards the train.
>> Cuz that's the way things happen in the
Polar Express. I love that book.
>> Yeah.
>> Oh my goodness.
>> Yeah. And there's something about that
like as a as a child wanting to step on
board for a magical adventure and going
somewhere. And that's kind of like what
stories do, isn't it? When you're a
child, you literally the power of a book
as a child. It's why so many like when
people talk about their favorite books,
there's always a children's classic in
there. I'll always talk about Winnie the
Pooh or, you know, because the books
that you read when you were younger.
>> What do you love about Winnie the Pooh?
Winnie the Pooh is a book I loved as a
child and then I loved again when I was
24 years old having a breakdown at my
parents house and I was agrophobic and I
couldn't leave the house and I just had
a load of children's books on the
shelves cuz they were my old books and
it was so comforting to read. I think
it's the ultimate self-help book that's
ever been written. You have to remember
a mil had been in the first world war.
He had been at the battle of Assam. He
had what we now call PTSD. He was going
through a lot of uh mental trauma. And
yet he wrote what is arguably the most
comforting book that and um house poo
corner two books and further stories
that were so comforting and so uh
fulfilling I think. And I think one of
the reasons is that every character in
those books is an archetype of a
different mental state. With our sort of
2020s language, you can go through and
give them all either
um mental health characteristic or a
neurode divergence quite easily. So
you'd have uh Piglet with anxiety,
Eeyore with depression,
Tiger ADHD,
Owl's dyslexia and narcissistic
personality who I would argue is an
addict, you know, for honey, gets
himself into all sorts of scrapes.
You've got Christopher Robin who's
having a uh mass hallucination event in
the forest. And so I I genuinely think
like he wasn't necessarily consciously
doing this, but I feel like 100 acre
wood
was created by a mil as his own kind of
like escape, the thing that could keep
him sane by escaping into this other
world. And I think often it's the most
uh troubled or difficult minds are
creating the most comforting stuff. You
always think that the sort of tortured
geniuses will create
the darkest,
strangest works, but often the impulse
is to go the other way is to create a
sort of lands where you feel safe and
comfortable.
>> Walk me through a little bit more of
having written children's stories, what
that showed you that then you applied
into novels for adults.
>> What isn't talked about a lot when
people talk about writing? um certainly
in traditional writing advice is
feeling. And I think feelings are
contagious. Very often what you're
feeling as you're writing is the feeling
that the reader has when they're
reading. So if you're feeling genuinely
happy and you're enjoying writing a
story, then
hopefully the reader at the end will
feel that. This is especially true true
with children's books. like you have to
like if you're writing a sort of silly
scene with some sort of rude elf or
something then you're writing that
scene. If if you're just writing it
because you have to write it and you
want to write a thousand words a day and
this is your thousand words then it's
not going to have that feeling. You've
got to enjoy what you're writing and it
will be better writing in that sense.
Um, editing is different obviously, but
when you're when you're creating the
bulk of that scene, you've got to try
and uh
feel what you're wanting the scene
to feel.
>> Is there room for excruciating agony and
maybe, hey, actually that is a good
place to write from, or is it like, no,
you got to process that and be somewhere
else?
>> No, I think so. I think obviously, you
know, like in art when people are
watching this the scream and standing in
front of it, then they're they're
feeling some of the sort of panic
disorder or whatever Monk was going
through, they're feeling some of that.
And I I feel like the same with books
and often often there's a comfort in
knowing a character or an author went
through something when you're reading
it.
>> When you're writing, do you think about
originality? One thing that I realized
very early on is that so many ideas you
think of are unique have been you know
done. There's a balance between
uh understanding that you know there are
no new stories in one sense. You know
the hero's journey and that those sort
of archetypes are there in lots and lots
of uh things. Yeah. the the ways of
telling them uh is is what's important
and the emotions carried through them um
are what's important. So you have to
think about uh originality. But with me
it's again it's an ADHD thing I think of
just not wanting to bore myself. One
thing that becomes harder as you as you
write uh more stories is is finding
newness within your own work even on a
simple level like
>> like it's even a originality contest
with yourself.
>> Yes. and you realize how much you've
already written, how many characters
names you've given, you know, like to
try, you don't want to call a character
something that you've called a character
in another book. The one character I
find hard to write, the one narrator I
find hard to write certainly is someone
who is like me, sort of like a
middle-aged man,
uh, like myself, I find very hard to
write. And in fact, the first draft of
the Midnight Library, it wasn't Norah
being the main character, it was a man
called Adam.
and I nearly gave up on the book just
because I could not see this person. And
I think it's like how sometimes you
don't know what you look like because
you've seen yourself too much. You you
know if you look at yourself in the
mirror or you look at a word too long,
it starts to lose its meaning. And I
think when I'm writing someone who is
basically me,
uh two things happen. one, it stops
being a character because it's just me
and you you don't really see yourself as
a character. You're just a very complex
state of existence. And then the other
thing that happened was
I was a bit guarded because it was me.
It was like writing non-fiction. So by
changing the gender, changing the age
and location a little bit as well, it
suddenly wasn't me. And therefore,
paradoxically, I put more of myself in
terms of my experience of mental illness
in terms of like feelings about regret
and guilt and that sort of stuff. More
of me went into this character as soon
as it wasn't me.
>> You said this that I thought was
interesting about sales numbers. If we
were number two in the bestseller
charts, the only book we would ever be
thinking about is the one selling more.
>> Well, I think I wrote that before.
I'd ever been number one for a start and
I wrote that in my 30s. I'm very
ambitious and um
I think
I don't know if that's a universal
thing, but that's definitely something
I've always felt in my career. There's
always another level that I'm looking up
to. As I've got older,
I've been more aware of that and I've
resisted it a little bit more. Um
because I I I I sensed a pattern in my
career where before I was published, I
thought I'm going to be happy forever if
I'm published. If I get my name on a
book, I will be happy forever. I'll be
satisfied. That validation will be there
forever. And you know, two weeks later,
there's something else. You want to be
on the tables in the bookstore. You want
to be in the window of the bookstore.
You want to be in the Sunday Times
bestseller list. or then you want to be
international. You want a foreign
publisher to take you on. You want to be
on their charts. You want to be on the
New York Times list. You want to be on
the number one of the New York Times
list. You want an adaptation because
someone else is having an adaptation.
You know, it's endless when you do that.
There's always when you're plugged into
that, there's always another level. And
I'm not saying it's totally useless
because it's it gives you drive and it
gives you a hunger, but you need to have
more than that. You need to have
something innate in you that wants to
articulate something. I think for a
while actually we think of ourselves as
ambitious in a very crude sense. But
when we delve into our ambition, it's
about something else. It's not just
about money or status in those crude
ways. And I think for me, my own
experience about mental illness and
being a troubled teenager played a big
part in in my ambition because I think
one of my incentives to write is to be
understood. So obviously if you're
selling a lot of books or you got a lot
of readers, then that gives you
something else. It makes you feel like,
oh, I'm accepted or I'm understood by
these people. I'm not that weirdo I once
thought I was or if I am a weirdo I
found these other weirdos who share
these weird thoughts. So I think that's
part of my ambition as well because I
realized I don't there were choices I
could have made certainly about 10 years
ago where I was offered like more money
by a bigger publisher in the UK to write
something that I wasn't 100% comfortable
with in terms of non-fiction
and I said no to it and I think since
then I've been quite proud to define my
career by what I'm saying no to as well
as what I'm saying yes to I'm saying
I've said no to a lot lots of things and
even to in terms of film adaptations and
things like that and I think you know
that's not a selfless thing that's not a
humble thing that is simply
not getting any kind of buzz or kick out
of doing stuff that doesn't feel like me
before I wrote uh novels I had a brief
career for about a couple of years
writing books about marketing and
business for a business publisher while
I was very far from being a business
person. But I was just a sort of jobbing
writer who'd written a column in a
magazine. I was writing a newsletter for
my girlfriend who was setting up a PR
company
and I got commissioned to write these
business books and it just felt so
pointless and such a drag to just write
words for the sake of writing words for
the sake of a check. And obviously it
needed the money and I don't resent
that. And it taught me some good things
about meeting deadlines and stuff like
that. But in terms of my own impulse to
write
during that time of writing stuff I
really didn't want to write my impulse
to write stuff I did want to write just
grew and grew and grew. So I think for
me now I understand what my ambition
was. My ambition was to be read
definitely I'm not one of those writers
who says I just write for myself. I
write to be read but to be read and
understood as me. So I don't really see
this difference. People say you know
like you either write for readers of for
yourself. No I write for readers
to understand
what's going on inside me. So I write to
be understood in a sense. So so writing
for readers I'm writing for myself is
kind of the same impulse.
talk to me about your relationship with
the publishing industry itself because
you referenced this Keats poem about the
sweet shop standing outside looking in
>> a sweet shop window and you know pressed
against a glass cuz uh yeah I used to
study like romantic literature at
university and I was always drawn to
Keats because even Keats by today's
standards would be seen as quite posh
and upper middle ass.
Um he he he was a little bit outside and
he was famously looked down on by Lord
Byron who called him like piss a bed
Keats and you know [laughter] you just
you just saw him writing about this sort
of delicate sort of like what he he he
seemed saw as sort of feminine stuff
rather than writing about wars and
heroes. And in terms of the publishing
industry
I've always uh I don't I don't really
know. I I I I think I struggled for a
while working out what type of writer I
am because I think in the UK especially
books are very related to uh class. I
was someone who when I was growing up I
never knew where I fit in personally and
I think this comes from my mom who was
adopted so she never knew her parents
and was very sort of class conscious. I
grew up in a working-class town. I was
considered quite posh because my mom was
a teacher, my dad was an architect.
And then you start writing books and
enter the publishing industry and think,
well, I didn't go to an expensive
school. I didn't go to the top
university. So, you know, you suddenly
feel like you're at the lower end. So, I
I I never knew my position. And in terms
of my own influences in terms of
writing, you know, at university, you
study all the sort of like your Virginia
Wolf, TSL,
um, everyone else. But my own influences
would be from everything from children's
books, choose your own adventure
stories, John Hughes movies,
>> Bourhees.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And, uh, Bourhees
definitely. I think in my early days
because I was published by a very
highbrow uh publisher uh for my first
three novels. I was very uh
self-consciously literary to an extent
that I wasn't being truly myself. Took
me to being sort of dropped and left a
little bit on the metaphorical scrappy
to actually find find myself. And I I
still wouldn't say I necessarily feel
like I I belong in any one particular
box, but I actually like that feeling.
Now,
>> let's end here. Stories are easy. The
plot of every book ever. Someone is
looking for something. The commercial
version, they find it. The literary
version, they don't find it. That's it.
>> Yeah. I mean, that is it. [laughter]
I think I think that's it. And I like
and there's a sort of commercial
literary version where they kind of find
it or they maybe find it in the next
unwritten chapter. But no, I I uh I I I
like to demystify uh the process. And
there's a I I think I feel like
sometimes the difference between
literary and commercial is the
difference between comfort and
discomfort. And it's like what's wrong
with comfort? What's wrong with hope?
what's wrong with a bit of positivity
from time to time. And you know, I think
it's very interesting often that it
comes from a certain type of like critic
this idea that sentimentality is the
very worst thing anything can be. I can
remember in the 1980s he was a music
magazine um which is still going but it
was enemy was like the bible in Britain
for sort of like bands and um the
critics could be very harsh.
>> What sticks out to me about that story
is trusting your instinct. You're like
but I just like the song.
>> That song has brought me so much joy in
my life. Like I don't care what the
critics have to say. And that probably
applies to my art too.
>> Exactly. Trusting feelings. trusting
your own feelings, trusting readers,
trusting yourself. I I I think it's
about that and not needing
a real or imaginary gateke keepers
approval before you can trust your own
opinions. And I think that's what you
need as a writer and possibly as a human
being, just that ability to kind of like
trust yourself.
>> Yeah. Yeah, I was talking to a friend
the other day who I think is an amazing
writer, an amazing writer. And I was
saying that I'd just gone to the Lou and
I didn't like it that much. And he goes,
"Yeah, cuz cuz 17th and 18th century
French painting is crap. There was
nothing good made in 200 years there."
And I don't know if he's right. I don't
know if he's wrong. He knows a lot about
art. But you know what? He trusts his
own taste enough to say something so
bold. and he can back it up in terms of
his knowledge of art history. And I was
like, that is cool to
be as in tune with your own sense of
what is good and bad, and not be so
caught up in what the critics have to
say, what society says you should and
shouldn't think.
>> Yeah. Or, you know, I tell I tell my son
this a lot cuz he'll go on like Reddit
and and work out what the collective
opinion is like. just what did you feel
when you listened to that or when you
read that? And that is your correct
response to that. And I try and remember
what I feel as I'm sort of sending off
my book before anyone's read it. What
what's my actual feelings about this?
Because it's so easy to have your mind
turned, you know, with that sort of
outward view, but you've got to sort of
like trust and be a bit stubborn. I
think you know writers can be quite
difficult people but that difficulty has
a use. It's to protect to put a boundary
around yourself to actually have those
battles with like commercial interests
or people pushing you one way or the
other way to actually say no I want to
do this.
>> Yeah.
>> Great to meet you Matt.
>> You too. Thank you. That was a good one.
Thank you.